<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of consumptions in which their      nature, causes and symptoms are briefly explained, and a new and extraordinary  method by specifick medicines is proposed for the cure of consumptions, even such as proceed from ulcers of the lungs / by Thomas Nevett ...</title>
            <author>Nevett, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N501B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24364852</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24364852</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52847)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1708:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of consumptions in which their      nature, causes and symptoms are briefly explained, and a new and extraordinary  method by specifick medicines is proposed for the cure of consumptions, even such as proceed from ulcers of the lungs / by Thomas Nevett ...</title>
                  <author>Nevett, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Astwood, and sold by Thomas Parkhurst ... and Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through and slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tuberculosis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lungs --  Diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109680:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF Conſumptions: IN WHICH Their Nature, Cauſes and Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms are briefly Explained; AND A New and Extraordinary Method by Specifick Medicines is Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the Cure of Conſumptions; even ſuch as proceed from Ulcers of the Lungs.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Nevett,</hi> Chyrurgion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Aſtwood,</hi> and Sold by <hi>Thomas Parkhurst</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> and <hi>Brabazon Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109680:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109680:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>I Remember a Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Paſſage in ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon the <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudas Berries,</hi> by a Dr. of Phyſick in the Country, addreſt to the Honourable <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Boyle,</hi> who profeſſeth he had been for fifty years an exact Obſerver of the
<pb facs="tcp:109680:3"/>
               <hi>Methodus Medendi,</hi> yet ſaith the Dr. for my part I firmly believe, that (<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Evacuations being premiſed) the greateſt Cures wrought in the World, are by the uſe of Specifical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. The higher the Attainments of any have been in underſtanding, the more freely have they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of thoſe things they did know, was the leaſt of thoſe things they did not know; ſuch men account
<pb facs="tcp:109680:3"/>it not ſhameful to renounce an Errour, tho' never ſo antient, when perſwaded thereunto by Truth and plain Demonſtration: There are other narrow Spirits (abundantly ſatisfied in their own knowledge) that believe the Art of Phyſick hath been taught by our Anceſtors, in ſuch an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect manner, as that nothing remains to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and Diligence of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; it being too much their Humour to underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
<pb facs="tcp:109680:4"/>every Medicine that they themſelves are not Maſters of, becauſe they prefer their private Intereſt to the publick Good: But in the mean time where is that cordial Love to Mankind, which is one of the Badges of true Chriſtianity? Nay, where is the Exerciſe of Reaſon? For how can a Man give his Opinion againſt a thing that he never heard of before, or at leaſt never experienced? I an ſure, this unjuſtifiable practiſe is
<pb facs="tcp:109680:4"/>the way to put a ſtop to all uſeful Knowledge and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements: It is therefore expected from the Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Candid Reader, that he ſhould adhere to Truths Cauſe, by whomſoever it is pleaded, weigh every In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, not in the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ballance of Cuſtom, but in the juſt and even Scales of Reaſon, approve what is agreeable, and reject what is contrary to it.</p>
            <p>That I who am by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion a Chirurgion, ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:109680:5"/>in ſuch a polite and inquiſitive Age, adventure my thoughts in publick concerning a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Caſe, may be to ſome matter of admiration, and to others of ſevere cenſure; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch as may think I have invaded their Province. As for the latter, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded nothing that I can ſay will remove their Prejudices, and for the former, I ſhall only tell them, that being ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramd by ſome of the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms mentioned in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe, whereby I
<pb facs="tcp:109680:5"/>plainly perceived the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my own Body inclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a conſumptive ſtate, I ſtrenuouſly applyed my mind iq ſtudy the Nature of this Diſeaſe, and to find out, if poſſible, ſome noble Specifick Medicines, which might indeed deſerve that Name, and be able to oppoſe the growth of ſo fatal a Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which hath inſenſibly flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ſo many into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Death. What I then laboured for, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after, I have ſince (by the
<pb facs="tcp:109680:6"/>Bleſſing of God) found, and with great advantage experimented on my ſelf and many others, and now think fit to diſcloſe for the good of all, not doubting but if a more Excellent Method and Medicine then hath hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been generally practiſed, or preſcribed, be treaſured up in the Hands of any Perſon whatſoever, he doth more faithfully perform the part of a juſt Steward, by a due Improvement, than a cloſe concealment of it. And on
<pb facs="tcp:109680:6"/>the ſame Account, I judge it more my Duty to Jerve my Native Country, than mind the Clamours of Cenſorious Criticks; not at all queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning but in a little time, the efficacy of theſe Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines will at once bring Health to the Patient, and Reputation to their Author: And when the World ſhall be convinced of the Power of theſe Remedies, by their Effects, I ſhall think it ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to make them known, which many will now be
<pb facs="tcp:109680:7"/>apt to contemn and neglect, until their Opinions be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by Experience, and their Prejudices removed by Demoſtration.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Houſe at the Chyrurgions-Arms in <hi>Fen Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> 
                  <date>Octob. 24. 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>T. Nevett.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109680:7"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF Conſumptions.</head>
            <p>THe Deſign of this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe is not to trouble the Reader with many Diviſions, or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions of Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109680:8"/>but briefly to enquire into the Nature and Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this Diſeaſe, as alſo to contribute my Mite, in order to oppoſe its Fury, by pointing at ſuch Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Medicines as are moſt likely to engage it with Succeſs.</p>
            <p>A Conſumption in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, is a waſting of all the ſolid parts of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for want of a due Diſtribution or Aſſimila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nutritious Juices.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109680:8"/>
            <p>By ſome Learned Men this is obſerved to be the Endemicall Diſtemper of <hi>England;</hi> and indeed our Weekly Bills at once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare both the greatneſs of the Diſeaſe, and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Medicines where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with its Cure hath been hitherto attempted. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that which ſeems to juſtifie this Obſervation, is the pernicious cuſtom of the Inhabitants of this Iſland, who immoderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unſeaſonably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109680:9"/>their Appetites with ſeveral ſorts of Meats and Drinks, whereby the Tone of the Stomach is ſo vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as that it cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ferment and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latilize the Chyle, which is commonly the internal procatartick cauſe of moſt Diſtempers among us, and conſequently of Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from thoſe Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, from whence comes a colliquation of the Chyle in <hi>Lienteries</hi> and <hi>Dyſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries,</hi> tormenting Colick
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109680:9"/>and Iliack Pains, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocondriack Melancholly, hyſterick Fits, ſcorbutick Twitches, troubleſom Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarrhs, ſluggiſh Paſſage of the Chyle through the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky Veins, ſcrophulous Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Inflammations of the meſenterick Glands, ſpaſmodick Contractions or Convulſions of the Nerves, preternatural Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the Blood and Spirits, <hi>Cachexys, Atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phys,</hi> Obſtructions, Feavers Hectical, inflammatory and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109680:10"/>putrid, Exulcerations of the Lungs and <hi>Maraſmus,</hi> with many other Diſeaſes, whence come they Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and for the moſt part, but from the Weakneſs, Ill Habit and Indiſpoſition of the Stomach?</p>
            <p>Now the proper Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Stomach is Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification; for though the Meat we take into our Mouths receives ſome alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration there in Maſtication, by the fermenting Juice that flows from the ſaliva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109680:10"/>Glands, together with the acrimonious Particles, and fermentaceous Spirits of Liquors which we drink, yet it is not turned into a thick white Juice, till it hath paſſed down through the <hi>Oeſophagus,</hi> or Gullet, into the Stomach, where by the help of its Fibres it is cloſely embraced, and mixed with ſpecifick fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaceous Juices, ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by its inner Coat, and impregnated by the Saliva, then by a convenient Heat
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109680:11"/>there is made a mixture of all; for that the fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taceous Particles entering into the Pores of the Meat, do paſs through, agitate and eliquate its Particles, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the whole <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> in which the purer parts were intimately uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Craſs, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them more fluid, ſo that they make another form of Mixture, and unite among themſelves into the reſemblance of a Milky Cream, after which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109680:11"/>with the thicker Maſs with which they are yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved, by the Conſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Stomach they paſs down to the Guts, where by the Mixture of the Bile and Pancreatick Juice they are by another manner of Fermentation quite ſeparated from the thicker Maſs, and ſo are received by the Lacteal Veſſels, as the thicker is ejected by ſtool.</p>
            <p>After the purer part of the Chyle hath been thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109680:12"/>ſtrained thorough the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and oblique Pores of the Milky Veins, by the continual and periſtaltick motion of the Inteſtines, it is yet further attenuated and diluted with a very thin and clear <hi>Lympha</hi> from the Glands of the Meſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery to expedite its paſſage through thoſe Numerous Meanders into the common Receptacle, from whence by the conſtant ſupply of ſuch like <hi>Lympha</hi> from the ſmall Glands of the <hi>Thorax,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109680:12"/>it is ſafely conveyed through the <hi>Ductus Chyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferus Thoracicus,</hi> ſubclavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Vein, and the <hi>Vena Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi> into the Heart.</p>
            <p>The Chyle now ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Blood, paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with it through the Arterys of the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and returns again with the Blood by the Veins to the Heart, undergoing many Circulations before it can be Aſſimilated to the Blood; for every time the new infuſed Chyle paſſeth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109680:13"/>through the Heart with the Blood, the Particles of the one are more intimately mixed with thoſe of the other, in its Ventricles, and the Vital Spirit, and other active Principles of the Blood work upon the Chyle, which being full of Salt, Sulphur and Spirit, as ſoon as its <hi>Compages</hi> is looſned by its Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Blood, the Principles having obtained the Liberty of Motion, do readily aſſociate themſelves,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109680:13"/>and are Aſſimilated with ſuch parts of the Blood as are of a like and ſuitable Nature.</p>
            <p>After the Chyle hath been thus Elaborated, it becomes fit as well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit the Maſs of Blood, as to Nouriſh the whole Body, ſeeing it conſiſts of divers Principles and Parts of a different Nature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Uſe and Neceſſity of every Part, and alſo that it may conform and faſhion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109680:14"/>it ſelf to the different Pores and Paſſages, ſo it is ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally appropriated, the moſt volatile and ſubtil part is ſeparated in the Brain, and adapted to refreſh the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits, the Glutinous to nouriſh the Body, and the Sulphureous to revive the Native Heat: And in its paſſage with the Blood through all the parts of the body, all the maſs of Chyle that is capable of being turned into Blood is ſanguified, the ſerous and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109680:14"/>ſaline part precipitated by the Kidneys, and evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Sweats or inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tranſpiration, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious is depoſited in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and the reſt of its Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements retire to the ſeveral Emunctorys of the Body.</p>
            <p>Thus it comes to paſs by the wonderful Sagacity of Nature, ſuch extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Proviſion is made, that the purer part of the Chyle by theſe ways and means is more purified; and when it is thus purified and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109680:15"/>it is more capable of reinforcing the Blood and Spirits, as alſo of corroborating the Tone of every particular Part: Whereas when the Chyle is ſowre and diſpirited, the blood neceſſarily becomes vappid, the Animal Spirits that reſide in the Syſtem of the Nerves are infected with a Morbid Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all parts of the Body begin to flag and waſte. For indeed there is no other way to recruit
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109680:15"/>the dayly Expence of Blood and Spirits, but by a continual Influx of lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Chyle into the blood-veſſels, which Chyle is made by the Fermentative Juice of the Stomach, and this Fermentative Juice ſupplyed from the Maſs of Blood, ſo that there plainly appears to be a fixt Correſpondence betwixt the Blood and Chyle, and a neceſſary Dependance all the Humours in the Habit of the Body have on the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109680:16"/>Stomach; from whence it is reaſonable to infer, That if the Chylifying Faculty of the ſtomach be depraved, the Blood and Humours muſt neceſſarily ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize therewith, and in a manner proportionable to the Diſtemper of this part.</p>
            <p>The immediate Cauſe of a Conſumption of the Lungs is ſtore of ſharp, malignant, wateriſh Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, continually diſtill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the ſoft ſpongy Subſtance of the Lungs,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109680:16"/>ſtuffing, inflaming, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumating, and exulcera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, whereby their Action, which is Reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a receiving in and driving forth Air is depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as will more clearly appear by the following Deſcription of theſe Parts. It may not be impertinent to our Diſcourſe if we ſhould uſher in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Lungs, with a ſhort account of the <hi>Trachea, Aſpera Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> or Wind-pipe.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109680:17"/>
            <p>The <hi>Trachea</hi> or <hi>Aſpera Arteria</hi> is a long Pipe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Cartilages and Membranes, which begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at the Throat or lower part of the Jaws, and lying upon the Gullet, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends into the Lungs, through which it ſpreads into many Branchings, and is commonly divided into two parts, the <hi>Larynx</hi> and <hi>Bronchus;</hi> the <hi>Larynx</hi> is the upper part of the Wind-pipe, the <hi>Bronchus</hi> is all the <hi>Trachea</hi> beſides the <hi>Larynx,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:109680:17"/>as well before as after it arrives at the Lungs.</p>
            <p>The Subſtance of the Lungs is ſoft, ſpongy and rare, curiouſly compacted of moſt thin and fine Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes, continued with the Ramifications of the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chea</hi> or Wind-pipe, which Membranes compoſe an infinite number of little, round and hollow Veſicles, or Bladders, ſo placed as that there is an open Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from the Branches of the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109680:18"/>one into another, and all terminate at the outer Membrane that inveſteth the whole Lungs : Theſe little Bladders by help of their muſcular Fibres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract themſelves in Expira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are dilated in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, partly by the preſſure of the Atmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere, and partly by the Elaſtick power of the Air, inſinuating it ſelf into theſe Veſicles through the Wind-pipe and its ſeveral branches: Their Lobes are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109680:18"/>two, the right and left, parted by the <hi>Mediaſtinum,</hi> each of which is divided into many leſſer Lobules, according to the Ramifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the <hi>Aſpera Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria;</hi> they have all ſorts of Veſſels that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them with other parts, as Arterys, Veins, Nerves, Lympheducts, but peculiar to themſelves they have their <hi>Bronchia,</hi> or the Branches of the Wind-pipe, for bringing in and carrying forth Air ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109680:19"/>to Life, that we cannot Live without it: And when we conſider their admirable Structure, (as well as the ſtructure of every individual part of our Body) how ought we to Adore the infinite Wiſdom of our Creator! Now when theſe ſmall Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicles or Bladders are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat with Extravaſated <hi>Serum,</hi> or purulent Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Natural Tone of the Lungs is ſo weakned, that we cannot enjoy the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109680:19"/>Benefit of free and full Reſpiration, hard, ſcirr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hous Tumours or Tuber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are bred, attended with a dry and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Cough, Oppreſſion of the Breaſt, difficult and ſhort Breathing, preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Heats, Exulcerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other deplorable Symptoms, according to the Degrees of Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and different Nature of the included Humours.</p>
            <p>The External Proca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tartick Cauſe of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109680:20"/>of the Lungs is cold Particles of Air, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtipating the Pores of the Body, whereby the <hi>Serum</hi> which ought to expedite the Motion, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Heat of the Blood is ſeparated from it, and thrown upon the Glands of the <hi>Larynx,</hi> and the ſpongy ſubſtance of the Lungs themſelves: For as the <hi>Lympha</hi> furthers the Motion of the Chyle, ſo the <hi>Serum</hi> accelerates the Circulation of the Blood,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109680:20"/>being carryed about with it through the ſmalleſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillary Veſſels and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt parts of the Body, leaſt it ſhould be inflamed with a burning Heat, or ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate by exceſſive thickneſs; during which circular moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they are both called by the ſame common Name, but when ſome Portion of <hi>Serum</hi> is ſeparated from the maſs of blood, and retreats to ſome one or more of the Emunctorys, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their various Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109680:21"/>it derives a Name from thoſe particular Parts on which it ſeizeth, as when it diſtils upon the Eyes, we call it <hi>Opthalmia,</hi> when upon the Noſe <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryza,</hi> and when upon the <hi>Thorax</hi> it goes by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Name of a <hi>Catarrh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for as much as there is nothing makes a Separation of the blood more commonly than the want of uſual Tranſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo nothing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth to the Preſervation
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109680:21"/>of Health, than that the Pores of the Body ſhould continually let forth the hot Steams and Vapours that ariſe from the Ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the blood; but when after taking Cold the Skin and Habit of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy are on a ſuddain ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up, that the ſulphure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wateriſh Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the blood cannot paſs through the Pores, they are again reſorbed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Maſs of Blood, from whence proceeds a Feaver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109680:22"/>Diſpoſition; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they are carryed off by Stool, or precipitated by the Kidneys, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tranſlated to the Glandulous Parts of the Lungs, where by Degrees contracting more and more Heat and Sharpneſs they inflame and exulcerate theſe tender parts.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs though a Conſumption of the Lungs is ſometimes thus cauſed by taking Cold, yet this comes to paſs but ſeldom, unleſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109680:22"/>in ſuch Bodys whoſe maſs of blood being rendered Cachectick, through fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Influxes of diſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chyle, is prediſpoſed to receive, and unable to free it ſelf from this New In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux of Catarrhous rheum: For ſuppoſe two Perſons in like manner deprived of the benefit of uſual Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration, by ſome great Cold, which though trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome in the beginning, becauſe of a violent and continual Diſtillation of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109680:23"/>Extravaſated <hi>Serum</hi> upon the Glandulous Coat of the Wind-pipe, and other adjacent Glands, yet in the one of theſe it ſurvives not the accidental Feaveriſh Diſpoſition of the Blood, occaſioned by the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of the Pores: For as ſoon as the Ferment ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the ſeparated humours, partly for want of a new Influx of <hi>Serum,</hi> and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Natural Heat of theſe parts, are concocted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thick ſort of Phlegm,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109680:23"/>and coughed up; after the Expectoration of which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated <hi>Serum</hi> the Glandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous parts preſently reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Natural Tone, without any Remains of a Tumour, Cough, Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Breath, or other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience; but in the other this Feaveriſh Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, occaſioned by taking Cold, is not tranſitory, but ſo Habitually fixed by means of ſome previous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition, as to increaſe the Efferveſcence and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109680:24"/>of the Blood and Spirits; from whence all the Glands which are ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the upper part of the <hi>Larynx,</hi> as alſo the Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Coat of the Wind-pipe it ſelf are overflown with a Deluge of hot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered Humours, the ſubſtance of the Lungs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtended with hard Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, the Branches of the Wind-pipe compreſt, and the Wind-pipe it ſelf from theſe Swellings irritated to Cough, by a continual
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109680:24"/>tickling, which promotes a frequent ſpewing out of hot ſharp Humours all along the <hi>Aſpera Arteria,</hi> till at length theſe Tuber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles growing very large, begin to inflame and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purate; immediately upon the breaking or open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Apoſtemes, ſometimes ſuch a flood of corrupted Matter is pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of their Baggs or Cavitys, into the Branches of the <hi>Trachea,</hi> as compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffocates and choaks
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109680:25"/>the Patient; but at other times this Purulent Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, mixt with ſtreaks of Blood, and ſome thin Phlegm that is continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharged from the Glandulous Coat of the Wind-pipe, is coughed up by degrees, and then this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Caſe requires Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Medicines, to cleanſe and heal theſe Ulcers.</p>
            <p>Such kind of Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whoſe Original is ſtore of malignant acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Humours, which are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109680:25"/>moſt apt to inflame and putrifie, may be termed Acute, when compared to others that proceed from Humours more mild and benign. There may be likewiſe ſome difference made by omitting Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and committing ſome egregious Errors in Dyet, Exerciſe, Paſſions of the Mind, or any other of the <hi>Non-Naturals:</hi> However, all Consumptions of the Lungs ought to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the number of Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109680:26"/>Diſtempers, becauſe they are contracted and augmented by degrees, and no other way to be reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died; yet this doth not prove them incurable in their own Nature, for Reaſon and Experience both teach the contrary: And indeed I muſt confeſs, it was from the marvelous Succeſs of theſe Remedies that I firſt imbibed this Notion, <hi>viz.</hi> Ulcers of the Lungs are in themſelves curable. Sometimes a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109680:26"/>or other Acute Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper may be jugulated, when either Nature or Art carrys off the Morbifick Matter by a ſuddain <hi>Criſis</hi> or plentiful Evacuation, but all hopes of diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a confirmed Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lungs inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are groundleſs ſeeing many inveterate Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be removed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of tough gluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Humous attenuated and evacuated, the whole Maſs of Blood and Spirits
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109680:27"/>rectified, the Habit of the Body meliorated, and the Tone of Several parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, before we can eradicate this fixed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</p>
            <p>What will be the Iſſue and Reſult of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Diſeaſe, may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be prognoſticated from its ſeveral Stages or Degrees: For when the Maſs of Blood by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Influx of ſowre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirited Chyle is reduced to a ſharp and Hectical
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109680:27"/>ſtate, and the <hi>Serum</hi> which is ſeparated from this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Blood only ſtuffs the Bladders and Glandules which are diſperſed through the body of the Lungs, this Diſtemper may be ſaid to be in its Infancy or beginning, (and if ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Remedies were then preſented, they might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an eaſie Conqueſt) but the increaſe is attended with a greater Diſtention of the Glands and Bladders, as alſo an Inflammation of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109680:28"/>theſe Tubercles tending to ſuppuration: For when the Animal Spirits which are neceſſary to the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fermentation of the Blood are vitiated with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome Particles of a Foggy and thick Air, and the Humour which for a long time hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Baggs or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitys of the Lungs is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heated by ſome extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Ebullition or Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the Blood, with a total ſuppreſſion of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109680:28"/>Expectoration, the Cough becomes more violent, the Feaver inflammatory, and all parts more tabid. In its further progreſs or ſtate all Symptoms advance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace towards their Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, Suppuration now ſucceeds the Inflammation of theſe Tubercles, for that the Purulent Matter is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breeding or already made, the Inflammatory Hectick is changed into a putrid Intermitting Feaver, attended with an Univerſal
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109680:29"/>Colliquation of the Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Juices and plentiful Separation of them from the Maſs of Blood by all ways of Evacuation that Nature affords; whence the Patients ſtrength ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly decays, and in a ſhort time he is reduced to the higheſt ſtate of a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus,</hi> with an <hi>Hippocratick</hi> Face.</p>
            <p>Thus having demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to the meaneſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity the greatneſs of this prevailing Evil, with its
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109680:29"/>efficient and material Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Reaſon it ſelf preſently ſuggeſts nothing leſs than great and noble Medicines can tame a Diſtemper ſo formidable. It is no leſs obvious to the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of every one that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth any thing of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, that the ſooner the Cure is begun the better, the more moderate the Patient is in the uſe of the ſix <hi>Non-Naturals,</hi> the more likely to ſucceed; the Spring time is the beſt Seaſon,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109680:30"/>Univerſals are to be premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Extraordinary Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms and Circumſtances peculiarly attended, and ſuch like things muſt run through the whole Courſe of Practiſe.</p>
            <p>No doubt but the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libeate Mineral Waters when impregnated with the Volatile Salts and Spirits of a ſerene Air, pleaſant Society, delightful Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Walks, regular Dyet, Freedom from Buſineſs,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109680:30"/>vexatious Thoughts, and the reſt may be ſerviceable: But if the Jeſuit were ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced to perpetual Exile, I think the Conſumptive have no reaſon exceſſively to lament, for I can tell them who hath a Febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge Antihectical, without a Grain of the Jeſuit, more excellent far than the <hi>Peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> Bark, becauſe it makes a ſafe, not a treacherous Peace, and can give a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of its working ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly, though they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109680:31"/>that know not how a thing can be done, think it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be done.</p>
            <p>For my part, I do not believe any Medicine can work a Cure in the way of a Charm, yet they that either know or uſe no other (at leaſt for the moſt part) than ordinary Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, cannot conceive how ſuch wonderful Effects can be wrought, unleſs by Enchantment.</p>
            <p>The common Method of Cure is by Phlebotomy,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109680:31"/>or Opening a Vein, to abate the Efferveſcence or Colliquation of the Blood, and prevent the Tumour and Inflammation of the Lungs, by Vomits to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Stomach oppreſt with ſtore of ill Humours, and remove divers Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of ſeveral Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and ſmall Veſſels, by Stomach-Purges gently to carry down the peccant Humours; and laſtly by Diureticks and Diapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks with ſome mixture
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109680:32"/>of an Opiate, plentifully to carry off the Colliqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Serum</hi> by Urine, or the Pores of the Skin, without raiſing a freſh Catarrh by a new Commotion of the Blood. After a due Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of theſe uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Evacuations, (which in their reſpective ſeaſons are highly neceſſary) the frequent Uſe of Pectoral Apozems and Pulmonary Linctuſſes is next enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to retund the Acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Humours that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109680:32"/>Ouze out by the Wind-pipe, by their mucilaginous and incraſſating quality, and ſo mitigate the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Cough. How far ſerviceable to this end and purpoſe the neateſt Forms of ſuch Diſpenſations that I ever yet ſaw may be, Ile not diſpute, only this I muſt take leave to ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to me (as alſo to the unprejudiced I humbly conceive) it ſeems evident, that ſuch fulſome Ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of which they are
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109680:33"/>compounded, are more apt to ſpoil a weak than reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a loſt Stomach, and conſequently not the fitteſt Medicines Conſumptive Perſons may have recourſe unto: For how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by woful Experience have found the conſtant and frequent uſe of ſuch Antiſtomachicks lead them from one Degree of this Malady to another, 'till their decaying Appetite hath been quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, (and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109680:33"/>their Hectick Heat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed) their Bodys ſo emaciated, as to render them uncapable of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Evacuations, and they themſelves at laſt given over to a Milk Dyet, Aſſes Milk, ſome Chalibeate Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Waters, or ſuch like Liquids, to which the poor diſtreſſed Stomach Ecchos aloud, Miſerable Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers all! If therefore I can, as I have Reaſon to believe, with Medicines leſs offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in Quantity, and more
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109680:34"/>uſeful in Quality, reſtore the loſt Appetite, and do the ſame, if not greater Service towards the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocting and Expectorating that load of ſeparated <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> with which the Pipes of the Lungs are ſtuffed, (which will eaſily be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Patient in a few Weeks, with due Care and Management) I think I have gained a great Point, for as much as the Recovery of the Stomach may reaſonably
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109680:34"/>be looked upon as an Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the Cure.</p>
            <p>The Medicines I do here recommend to my Countrey-men as Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficks in the Cure of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions of the Lungs, ariſing from the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Cauſes, have a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Faculty of warming, comforting and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weak Stomachs, attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating and gently carrying off that load of Tartareous Matter which is lodged in their rugous Coat, depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109680:35"/>both Appetite and Digeſtion. In their Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through the whole circumference of the Guts, they likewiſe diſſolve that cruſted Slime and Filth which hinders the Preſſure of the Chyle into the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky Veſſels by the Periſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick motion of their Spiral Fibres: Thus having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved theſe Fundamental Obſtructions, they haſten together with the Chylous Mixture, which by this time is ſomewhat Invigora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109680:35"/>towards the Relief of the Sanguineous Maſs, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon their Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction the Blood revives, and by degrees becomes brisk and vigorous, able to cope with, and give ſome check to the preter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Hectick Heat, ſtop the Influx of Rheum into the Glandulous Subſtance of the Lungs, concoct that which is already collected, and releaſe the Animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, intangled with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious diſpoſition of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109680:36"/>Nervous Juice. Having gained theſe Advantages, things begin to look with another manner of Aſpect, the Habit of the Body grows firmer, the Mind chearfuller, the Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance freſh and brisk, the Emaciated Parts gather Fleſh and Strength, the Lungs and Glands of the <hi>Larynx</hi> recover their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Tone, and the whole Conſtitution improves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a State of Health. Moreover, Theſe <hi>Antiph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſicks</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:109680:36"/>are really impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with ſuch Volatile Spirits and Salts, that like unto Lightning they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate the remoteſt Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Body, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating the very Seeds and Roots of this grievous Diſeaſe, powerfully and effectually, yet pleaſantly and ſecurely, if plentifully taken in the manner of a Dyet: For thus in time they chear up the drooping Animal Spirits, fortifie the Syſtem of the Nerves, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109680:37"/>ſo influence the whole San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guineous Maſs, as that the Blood it ſelf becomes the moſt precious of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Balſoms, marvellouſly cleanſing the putrid Ulcers of the Lungs, and finally reducing them to a perfect <hi>Cicatrix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore let none be deceived by the flattering Nature of this Diſtemper in the beginning, nor give themſelves over for loſt in the higheſt ſtate, becauſe theſe reviving Cordials are
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109680:37"/>calculated for the weakeſt Conſtitutions, ſeeing at the ſame time they offend the Diſeaſed Matter with the one hand; they ſupport Nature from ſinking under any Evacuations with the other. It is therefore my Advice to the Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or conſumptively in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, and their Intereſt (by way of Prevention) to acquaint themſelves in time with theſe Soveraign Antidotes. Better Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel I cannot give to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109680:38"/>beſt of my Friends, if they are deſirous to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a great deal of Pain and Miſery, as well as Charges, and render their Lives comfortable to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and ſerviceable to others.</p>
            <p>The Warmneſs of theſe Medicines, which is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Objection that ever I met with in the uſe of them, is ſo far from being a real Diſcouragement, as that upon ſerious and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Considerations it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109680:38"/>becomes a Notable Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to enforce the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would be too weak to engage the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Cauſe of Hectick, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Putrid Feavers; whereas by this active Principle of Heat, they work ſo effectually upon the whole maſs of Chyle, as to ſeparate the ſharp and diſpirited from the Nutritious Particles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, thoroughly inſinuate themſelves into all the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109680:39"/>Avenues of the Adverſary, cut and divide the tough viſcous Humours that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper the Veins, Arteries and Nerves, deſtroy the Acidity of the Nervous Juice, recover the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Temper of the Animal Spirits, ſweeten the maſs of Blood, by ſeparating the Impurities thereof by the Cutaneous Glands, gently forcing a Tranſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Feaveriſh Particles of the whole, and ſo baniſh that Preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109680:39"/>Heat which is Proof to all common Remedies. And that Diſeaſes which carry in their outward appearance a ſhew of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural Heat are thus to be treated with warm Medicines, is indeed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable to every diſcerning Eye: For the moſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Feavers are attackt and conquered by the briskeſt and warmeſt <hi>Alexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharmacks</hi> and the moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent <hi>Eryſipelas,</hi> or St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi>'s <hi>Fire,</hi> is diſcuſſed and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109680:40"/>breathed out by ſtrong and Spirituous Fomentations, but are both of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated by refrigerating or cooling Medicines, and their preternatural Heat more and more increased, till the one at length ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates in the cold ſweats of Death, and the other in a compleat Mortification.</p>
            <p>To multiply Inſtances of this kind is remote from my intended brevity, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take this remarkable one for all: The Wife
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109680:40"/>of Mr. <hi>Fowles,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the <hi>Mint</hi> in the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>November,</hi> 1695. ſent for me to open a Vein; after a lamentable Complaint that ſhe was nothing the better, but the worſe for all the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſhe had taken: I took leave, wiſhing her to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Patience, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the uſe of thoſe things the Dr. had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; though I alſo told her, if ſhe found no Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109680:41"/>I would do her all the Service I could, if ſhe ſent for me: About the middle of <hi>January</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe did ſend for me again, and told me Dr. <hi>H.</hi> her Phyſician, and Mr. <hi>W.</hi> Apothecary, had given her over, therefore deſired ſome Aſſiſtance, according to my Promiſe: I found her in a very low Condition, under a Hectick Feaver, troubleſome Cough, tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Aſthma, Colliquative Looſneſs, with a Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109680:41"/>of Convulſive and Epileptick Fits, (of which ſhe had ſometimes to the Number of Eighteen or Twenty in a day) Total Deprivation of Appetite, having for ſome Months together received no other ſuſtenance from Food, than what a Glaſs of Sack with a Toast afforded, whereby all the Parts of her Body were waſted and conſumed to the higheſt degree of a <hi>Maraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> that ever I ſaw, resemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a walking Ghoſt, or a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109680:42"/>perfect Skeleton, inveſted with nothing but Skin. For my part I was not very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to do any thing, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few days would put a period to her Life; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed was the Seaſon any ways inviting: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the good Opinion ſhe was pleaſed to entertain of my Endeavours, encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me more than I could her, and with the Bleſſing of God on both Method and Medicines, without any aſſiſtance from the Bark or
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109680:42"/>Mineral Waters, ſhe was quite freed from her Hecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cd Heat, her Fits abated almoſt every day, her Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach returned, her Bones wire cloathed with Fleſh, and her Strength ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited, as that ſhe was able to walk ſeveral Miles toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without a Supporter, though ſhe could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change the unwholſome, foggy, <hi>Tower</hi> Air, (at this time more than ordinarily polluted with ſtore of naſty black Particles, from the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109680:43"/>ſmoak of Coals) for the freſh clear Country Breez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, till the latter end of Summer. Before and ſince this proſperous Event I have given theſe Remedies to others, and taken them my ſelf ſeveral hundreds of times, and have always found then Operations in offenſive, for the moſt part ſucceſsful, and sometimes wonderful.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109680:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
